Inventory of the Maupin-Washington Papers 1732-1932
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Personal and Business Correspondence of Peter Grayson Washington, 1835-1866, n.d. (Box 1-2)
  - Personal and Business Correspondence, 1861., 13 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Tho[ma]s J[efferson] Barr, New York, [New York], to Col. Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 7 January 1861., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Discusses purchase of a building by the Post Office.
    - A[lfred] B[urton] Greenwood, Commissioner, Office [of] Indian Affairs, Department of the Interior, to Peter Grayson Washington, Washington, D.C., 11 January 1861., 1 page. LS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Discusses Victoria Angi's claim for land in the Lake Pepin Sioux Halfhreed tract.
    - Joseph Lane, Washington, D.C., to Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 21 January 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Sends a letter from John Anderson.
    - J[ames] R. Powell, Montgomery, Alabama, to Col. Peter Grayson Washington, Washington, D.C., 7 May 1861., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Has had conversations with "high officials" on his usefulness in establishing a new government; discusses status of U.S. postal officials in the Confederacy; mentions Quintus [Washington?].
    - J[ames] R. Powell, Montg[omer]y, Alabama, to [Peter Grayson] Washington, n.p. 24 June [18]61., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Inquiries about how to safely go to Washington, [D.C.] to settle with the Post Office Department; gives his views of the [Civil] War, and its possible outcomes.
    - J[ames] R. Powell, Montgomery, Alabama, to [Peter Grayson] Washington, n.p., 23 July 1861., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Discusses sentiment toward the [Civil] War, and how to receive his back pay; needs help in getting a nephew home from St. James College in Maryland.
    - Jno. Harrington[?], Ass[istan]t Secretary of the Treasury, [Washington, D.C.], to C. Ingle, Washington, D.C., 21 August 1861., 1 page. PDS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Form letter stating that his letter has been received, and his money referred for settlement.
    - Edward Cooper, New York, [New York], to Peter Grayson Washington, Washington, D.C., 7 September 1861., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Lists the stocks and bonds, mainly railroads and municipalities, in the package he is keeping for him; wants information on the iron-plated ship project for which bids were recently opened.
    - Tho[ma]s J. Barr, New York, [New York], to Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 8 November 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Discusses a building to be sold to the government.
    - Tho[ma]s J. Barr, New York, [New York], to Col. Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 9 December [18]61., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Discusses papers on a certain building.
    - John M. Read, 1119 Chestnut St., [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania?], to Peter Grayson Washington, Continental [Hotel?], 9 December 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Invitation for dinner.
    - Tho[ma]s J. Barr, New York, [New York], to Col. Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 14 December 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Owners of a certain building have a chance to rent the upper floors, so he needs to know if the government will buy it.
    - Tho[ma]s J. Barr, New York, [New York], to Col. Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 21 December 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Has had no reply to his last two letters.
  - Personal and Business Correspondence, 1862-1866., 11 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
    - John Cadwalader, Philad[elphi]a, [Pennsylvania], to Col. [Peter Grayson] Washington, n.p., 3 February 1862., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Inquires about Mr. Gerard's chances of being named consul; mentions his son, Charles.
    - Tho[ma]s J. Barr, New York, [New York], to Col. [Peter Grayson Washington], n.p., 7 May 1862., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Discusses some stock; inquires about the recipient's "banking business."
    - Tho[ma]s J. Barr, New York, [New York], to Col. [Peter Grayson Washington], n.p., 18 May 1862., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Discusses the stock in the "Central Park North and East River Rail Road Co.," which he purchased for Washington.
    - Tho[ma]s J. Barr, New York, [New York], to Col. [Peter Grayson Washington], n.p., 28 May 1862., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Thanks him for his picture.
    - Tho[ma]s J. Barr, New York, [New York], to Col. [Peter Grayson Washington], n.p., 2 June 1862., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Describes a bank charter that is for sale.
    - Tho[ma]s J. Barr, New York, [New York], to Col. [Peter Grayson Washington], n.p., 25 July 1862., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Discusses prospects of Hudson River Rail Road stock.
    - Tho[ma]s J. Barr, New York, [New York], to Col. [Peter Grayson Washington], n.p., 30 July 1862., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Fears previous letter of July 25 was lost, so summarizes its contents; enlistments are slow [in New York City], but better in other parts of the state.
    - W. L. Gaylord, Packwaukee, Marquette County, Wisconsin, to Col. Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 16 November 1863., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Requests help for his son, Isaac B. Gaylord of Co. K, 10th Regt., Wisconsin Volunteers, who was taken at Chickamauga, and who is a prisoner at Richmond, [Virginia]; his son also needs boots and blankets; if he [Peter Grayson Washington] cannot help, perhaps C. S. Drew or George Snelling can.
    - Geo[rge] P. Kane, [Midway?], to Col. Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 26 January 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Plans to visit tomorrow, although it may tax the "Charlottesville transportation department."
    - Edw[ar]d B. White, Charleston, South Carolina, to Ja[me]s Guthrie, n.p., 14 July 1866., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Was architect of the Customs House at Charleston; requests assistance in getting a pardon for his service as a Col. of Artillery in the Confederate Army.
      This letter was included with the letter listed below; Edw[ar]d B. White, Charleston, South Carolina, to Col. Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 14 July 1866.
    - Edw[ar]d B. White, Charleston, South Carolina, to Col. Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 14 July 1866., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Requesting Washington's assistance in getting a pardon.
      This letter was included within the above letter; Edw[ar]d B. White, Charleston, South Carolina, to Ja[me]s Guthrie, n.p., 14 July 1866.
    - Edw[ar]d B. White, Charleston, South Carolina, to Col. Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 26 July 1866., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Gives details of his application for pardon; mentions his wife and daughter.
  - Personal and Business Correspondence, n.d., 7 items. (Box-folder 2:7)
    - H[enry] May, Balt[im]o[re, Maryland], to Col. [Peter Grayson] Washington, n.p., 18 February n.y., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Sends an assignment regarding money belonging to his orphaned nieces; asks for a list of the Texas bond or script owners.
    - M. H. Grinnell, n.p., to Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 13 March n.y., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Asks for copies of the Emigrant Bill.
    - J. M. Corbit, n.p., to Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 27 March n.y., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Thanks him for the note of introduction for Corbit's mother-in-law, Mrs. Macleod, and her two nieces, who were afraid of being accused of smuggling after returning home from a Parisian education.
    - E[dward] Cunard, 4 Bowling Green, to Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 25 May n.y., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Hopes they can change their dinner engagement to Thursday, as he needs to see Mr. [Gouverneur] Kemble at Cold Spring on Wednesday.
    - H[enry] May, Balt[im]o[re, Maryland], to Colonel [Peter Grayson Washington], n.p., 13 June n.y., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Inquires about the steamboat Osmise [?] for Mr. Walsh.
    - Ro[bert] Tyler, n.p., to Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., 14 August n.y., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Reminds him of Tyler's "Revenue Agent Case"; "after a pretty hard life, it gives me a chance to stand straight up"; reports that [John] Cadwallader is well.
    - N. Turnbull, B[reve]t Colonel, n.p., to Peter Grayson Washington, n.p., n.d., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Introduces Mr. Bowditch.
  Series 2: Maupin Correspondence
- Maupin Correspondence, 1850-1872., 12 items. (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Lund Washington, Washington City [D.C.], to Doctor Socrates Maupin, Richmond, Virginia, 22 September 1850., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Discusses his family, especially Peter Grayson Washington and Quinton Washington; market has a good supply of fruits and vegetables; suggests newspapers for ads for the Medical College [of Virginia].
  - Silas Totten, Williamsburg, [Virginia], to S[ocrates] Maupin, M.D., n.p., 12 February 1852., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Cannot lecture before the Atheneum at the time suggested, because Bishop Johns will be away, so he must stay to attend the religious services at the College [of William and Mary], and officiate at the church in town [Bruton Parish Church]; would be able to lecture on Mental Philosophy in March.
  - Millard Fillmore, Executive Mansion, Washington, [D.C.], to S[ocrates] Maupin, Richmond, Virginia, 31 January 1853., 1 page. L. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Form letter informing Maupin of the awarding of an Exhibitor's Medal for his exhibit of Minerals at the 1851 Exhibition of the Works of all Nations in London; also signed by Peter Force.
  - [?], to [Socrates?] Maupin, University of V[irgini]a, [Charlottesville, Virginia], 186[?]., 1 page. Telegram. In German. (Box-folder 3:1)
  - H. R. Sutton, Virginia Land Office, Richmond, [Virginia], to "Dear Sir," n.p., 186[?]., 1 page. LS. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Summary of Military Warrants issued to Lund Washington in 1838.
  - Richard L. Maury, Fredericksburg, Virginia, to Dr. S[ocrates] Maupin, University of Virginia, [Charlottesville, Virginia], 28 July 1860., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Discusses a resolution of the Faculty of the University in light of conversations between them during the disturbances in May; demands that he have the resolution rescinded.
  - Peyton Randolph, Capt. Com[man]d[in]g, H[ea]d Qu[arters], Camp [sic] [Fort] Gilmer, [Virginia], to Lt. Col. T. M. R. Talcott, Com[man]d[in]g 1st Eng[inee]r Regt., n.p., 21 January 1864., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Encloses descriptions of 17 men who deserted "last night," and asks that the list be forwarded to Lt. [?] Maupin, the recruiting officer at Raleigh, [North Carolina]; also asks for cartridges because he feels it will help morale if the guard has loaded arms.
    This letter was included with the letter listed below; T. M. R. Talcott, H[ea]d Qu[arter]s, 1st Eng[ineers] Regt., 21 January [1864].
  - T. M. R. Talcott, H[ea]d Qu[arter]s, 1st Eng[ineers] Regt., 21 January [1864]., 1 page. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Ordering Lt. [?] Maupin to take steps to notify the proper officers about the deserters.
    This letter was included within the above letter; Peyton Randolph, Capt. Com[man]d[in]g, H[ea]d Qu[arters], Camp [sic] [Fort] Gilmer, [Virginia], to Lt. Col. T. M. R. Talcott, Com[man]d[in]g 1st Eng[inee]r Regt., n.p., 21 January 1864.
  - C[hapman] M[aupin], Camp [sic] [Fort] Gilmer, [Virginia], to Robert [W. Maupin], c/o Dr. S[ocrates] Maupin, University of Virginia, [Charlottesville, Virginia], 12 February [18]64., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Thanks his brother for the overcoat; regiment has been guarding Yankee prisoners at Belle Isle, and will be detailed to escort the prisoners to Georgia; is tired of being near Richmond; needs shoes; saw Capt. E[?] Grayson, whose son Willie is going to school "in town"; asks for a bottle of [?] for Capt. S. T. S.[?].
  - Howzer & Hendrix, [?], to Dr. S[ocrates] Maupin, n.p., 22 July 1865., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Notification that much of his cotton has been stolen "since the occupation of this country by the Federal troops"; asks him to send someone to see the situation.
  - S. D. Cabaniss, Huntsville, Alabama, to Dr. S[ocrates] Maupin, Prof[essor] of Chemistry, University of V[irgini]a, [Charlottesville, Virginia], 20 September 1867., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Introduces Richard W. Walker, who is visiting Virginia to find schools for his son and daughter; asks for the same attention to Walker's son as was shown his son, Charles.
  - Chapman [Maupin, Berlin, Germany], to "Father," Professor S[ocrates] Maupin, University of Virginia, [Charlottesville, Virginia], 5 March [18]70., 12 pages. ALS. Including Ms. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Mentions his courses in classical studies; discusses Mr. Schele's[?] proposal [that C. M. teach languages]; refers to many [European?] and American professors; describes the organization of Prussian universities; mentions other University of Virginia students studying in Berlin, including Garnett, Hill, and Gallaher; American dislike of George Bancroft in Berlin; reaction to a divorce case in England involving the Prince of Wales [later Edward VII]; arrival of "the Siamese twins"; discusses where in Europe to look for information on their family.
    Including Ms., n.d., of notes on the Washington genealogy. 2 pages.
  - S[usan] M[onroe] G[rayson] Maupin, University of V[irgini]a, [Charlottesville, Virginia], to "Mother," Mrs. S[allie] W[ashington] Maupin, [Baltimore, Maryland], 11 November 1872., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Describes a visit from Mr. [John Barbee] Minor, who wants detailed information on father's [Socrates Maupin] life; describes her cold; sends best wishes to other relatives.
  Series 3: Genealogical Information
- Genealogical Information, 1889-1891. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - 7 letters between Moncure D. Conway, New York, [New York], and Professor [Chapman] Maupin, [Baltimore, Maryland]. 16 April 1889 - 19 February 1891., 7 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
    The letters concern Lund Washington, his papers and his family
    Also includes 1 ALS on the same subject from Worthington C. Ford, Brooklyn, New York, to Chapman Maupin, n.p., 4 October 1891, enclosing a chart of the descendents of Lawrence Washington.
  - Handwritten and typed copies of wills of Lawrence Washington, Lund Washington, and Thomas Washington, n.d. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Chart of the "Washington Ancestry" compiled by Edward S. Lewis, n.d. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - "Ancestry of Chief Justice Marshall," n.d., 1 page. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Typed article on John Marshall, n.d. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Handwritten article on the ancestry of Mrs. Robert G. Hogan[?], an officer, of the Maryland D.A.R., n.d., 3 pages. (Box-folder 3:2)
  Series 4: Deeds and Other Items Relating to the Exchange of Land
- Deeds and Other Items Relating to the Exchange of Land, 1732-1842. (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Thomas and Mary Wallis, Hamilton Parish, Prince William County, [Virginia], to "brother" Burr Wallis, n.p., 1 March 1732., 1 page. DS. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Deed to parcel of land, part of that taken up by their father, John Wahhis.
  - Spence Grayson, William Grayson, and John Hedgman, Virginia, to Benjamin Grayson, son of Spence Grayson, Virginia, 23 October 1783., 3 pages. DS. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Appointment to survey lands in western Virginia, and agreement to give him a portion of those lands.
  - Al[exander] McRae, n.p., to Lewis M. Rivalain, n.p., 3 April 1805., 2 pages. DS. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Agreement to sell land "on the street leading by the Swan tavern (commonly called the main street on Shockoe Hill," [Richmond, Virginia]), purchased from Dr. Philip Turpin with receipt for £l8O of the £200 purchase price. Witnessed by W[illia]m Price, William] West, and Cha[rle]s Blagrove.
  - Doctor Philip Turpin and Martha [Turpin], Chesterfield County, [Virginia], to Lewis M. Rivalain, Richmond, [Virginia], 24 February 1806., 3 pages. DS. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Deed to parcel of land on main street on Shockoe Hill, Richmond, [Virginia], "opposite the ... house of Daniel Call"; sold for £200 (Virginia money); witnesses: John S. Ellis, Robert Priddy, Morris Cosby, and John Allan; land is further described in relationship to Smith's "yellow house," the Swan tavern, "Harris the coach-maker's shop," and Alexander McRae's "carriage house."
  - William W. Worsley and Rebecca Worsley, Thomas Smith, and James and Tabitha Smith Parish, Fayette County, Kentucky, to Peter Crutchfield, Richmond, Virginia, 13 April 1812., 8 pages. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Letter includes the items listed below.
    - Deed to rights in Lot 779 in Richmond, [Virginia], 3 April 1812. (Box-folder 3:3)
      This deed formerly belonged to Samuel Smith, late husband of Tabitha Smith Parish; lot further described in relationship to property of Alexander McRae, and Lewis M. Rivelain [sic] [Rivalain].
    - Two signed documents concerning the examination of Rebecca Worsley and Tabitha Parish, 13 April 1812., 3 pages. 2 DsS. (Box-folder 3:3)
      One being a Court order, 13 April 1812, from the General Court of Virginia to the Justices of the Peace in Kentucky, ordering examination of Rebecca Worsley and Tabitha Parish, and the other a certificate of examination, 13 April 1812.
    - Signed document of Ch[arle]s Scot t, Governor of Kentucky, stating that Price Curd and Leonard Young were, at the time of examination, Justices of Fayette County, Kentucky, 28 April 1812., 1 page. DS. (Box-folder 3:3)
    - Bill of Exchange for $700 from W[illia]m W. Worsley, Lexington, Kentucky, to Peter Crutchfield, Richmond, Virginia, 5 June 1812., 1 page. DS. (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Robert Saunders and Robert Nelson, Commissioners in 2 suits in Chancery District Court of Staunton, [Virginia], 4 May 1814., 5 pages. DS. (Box-folder 3:3)
    The first suit was between Samuel W. Barrett and William Hylton, Senior, William Hylton, Jun[io]r, Mehitable Campbell, George Lawrence, Luke Tiernon; and the second was between Daniel L. Hylton, and William Foushee and Samuel W. Barrett, William Hylton senior and Miles King, to William Foushee, Richmond, [Virginia]. Deed to land and mill in Warwick County, [Virginia], called "Rich-Neck Estate" for $15,000.00, with summary of payments and endorsements in Williamsburg and Warwick County courts.
  - James and Ann Maria Taylor, n.p., to Peter V. Daniel and James Rawlings, n.p., 13 May 1817., 3 pages. DS. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Mortgage to part of Lot 7 in Petersburg, [Virginia], with endorsements in courts in Richmond and Petersburg, [Virginia].
  - William Watts Gwathmay, acting through James Temple Doswell, n.p., to James D. Morris, n.p., 31 December 1842., 4 pages. DS. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Deed to land in Galveston County, Republic of Texas, with endorsements by Louisiana and Texas courts.
  Series 5: Miscellaneous Material
- Miscellaneous Material, 1771-1932, n.d. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - George Washington, Camp at Cambridge, [Massachusetts], to Richard Henry Lee, 29 August 1775. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - B[enjamin] Franklin, London, [England], to Humphry Marshall, West Bradford, Chester County, 22 April 1771. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Theodore D. Woolsey, Pres[iden]t, Yale College, [New Haven, Connecticut], to [?], 20 December 1854., 1 page. ANS. (Box-folder 3:4)
    Notice that [?] Luckett "of the Freshman Class" is dismissed honorably and without censure "at his Father's Request."
  - George Minor, Comman]d[e]r in charge, Office of Ord[inance] & H[ea]d q[uarters], Richmond, Virginia, to Frank Minor, Exchange Hotel, Richmond, [Virginia], 27 May 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
    Sends description of percussion caps for small arms and has sent him fuses and caps.
  - [?], Acting Secretary, Department of the Interior, Washington, [D.C.], to A[ndrew] G. Chapman, La Plata, Maryland, 23 May 1883., 1 page. TLS. (Box-folder 3:4)
    Reports that none of the documents on N[orth] A[merican] Ethnology, which he requested from the Chief Clerk of the House of Representatives, can be supplied by the Department of Interior.
  - A Latin Primer, 1889., 1 item. PV. (Box-folder 3:4)
    Introductory to Gildersleeve's Latin Series. Revised by the author and Chapman Maupin.
  - 2-cent stamps honoring the Sesquicentennial Exposition, 1926., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Menu/Program of the Celebration of the 200th Anniversary of the birth of George Washington, 1932., 4 pages. PM. (Box-folder 3:4)
    Sponsored by the George Washington Bi-Centennial Commission of Baltimore, [Maryland].
  - Various clipped autographs, n.d. (Box-folder 3:4)
    Clipped autographs include the following:
    J. R. Barret
    Noble S. Braden
    Benj[amin] S. Ewell
    James B. Fever[?]
    D. Funsten
    John Maclean
    T. F. Mayard
    W[illiam] J. Robertston
    J. R. Rucker
    D. L. Swain
    Dawson S. Walker
  Series 5: Photographs
- Photographs, 1922, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Carte de visite of Edwin Booth, n.d. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Carte de visite of a cartoon entitled The Great Matrimonial Admonisher and Pacificator, n.d. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Office in Clark County, Virginia, where [George] Washington stayed when surveying for Lord Fairfax. August 1922., Photographic Print. Black and White. 8x10 (Box-folder 3:4)